We are now in the we have begun the third פרק, perek,
we pick up at the top of ל"ד ע"א. Lamed Dalet Amud
Alef. The משנה mishna which we'll be focusing on speaks about, sort
of takes for granted this פרק perek this פרק perek is going
to be devoted to issues of שומרים shomrim and like the first
פרק perek of the מסכת masechet which was it's devoted the first
two פרקים prakim were devoted to issues of מציאה, metzia, finding lost
objects, but the first one rather than laying out basic parameters went
to special cases, this פרק perek as well rather than laying out
basic parameters of the situations under which שומרים shomrim are liable, take
a שבועה, shevua, have to pay and so on, it immediately begins
with special cases and deals with the issue of somebody who a
שומר shomer presumably it's a שומר חנם shomer chinam who the object
was stolen נגנב nignav actually burgled and is entitled to take an
oath that he was not negligent and be exempt, but rather than
take an oath he agrees to pay. And it's not clear in
the משנה mishna but we'll see in the גמרא gemara there are
two scenarios he can agree to pay: he could admit that he
was negligent and therefore he says 'I'm not going to swear falsely,
I was negligent, I'm going to pay, that's my legal obligation'. Or
there's a scenario where he could basically say 'I wasn't negligent, but
you know, I'd rather just make good with the owner, I don't
want to take שבועות, shevuot, I feel, you know, it was my
responsibility at the end of the day even though legally I'm not
liable, I'm going to pay the owner, I'm not going to take
an oath'.
And so and then the גנב ganav is found. So the משנה
mishna teaches that in the case that the שומר shomer agrees to
pay rather than take a שבועה, shevua, the גנב ganav will pay
the כפל, kefel, the double, or even four and five if it
was an animal that was slaughtered, and he'll pay it to the
שומר. shomer. So what is the logic for this? I mean it
was the owner's object, it wasn't the שומר's shomer's object. The שומר
shomer is liable for loss, but why is the גנב ganav paying
the double or the four and the five to the שומר? shomer?
So the most logical thing to say is that this is some
type of a rabbinic תקנה takana for like if you want to
call it תיקון עולם tikkun olam or just you know for the
best interest of all parties involved. Like the owner's primary concern is
getting his object back and therefore they're going to incentivize שומרים shomrim
should grease the wheels of the owner getting his money back by
sort of saying 'you know what, if you're if you're if you're
sort of willing to you know just pay the owner back and
save everybody all the effort and not stand on your right to
take a שבועה shevua and all of that, you might actually get
some benefit out of this in a case at least in the
case of גניבה, gneiva, you know, you can get double, you can
get four and five'. So anyway again I'm not sure how strong
of a motive that is, and it only works in cases of
גניבה, gneiva, but nevertheless it's like the owners are much more interested
in knowing that they like a bird in the hand is worth
two or four or five in the bush, you know, the owner
is much more willing to just get simply simplify getting paid back.
So that would be understood as a תקנה. takana.
In the case for the court system also. Right, so to save
the
בית דין.
beit din.
Exactly. Correct, it's good for the court system as we're going to
see, people don't have to שלעפ shlep to בית דין, beit din,
clog up the court. Anyway, that's seen as a תקנה. takana. At
the beginning of the גמרא gemara and that might actually be an
opinion that comes up later and it's certainly an opinion in the
ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, but the סתם stam of the גמרא, gemara, the beginning
of the גמרא gemara that we saw yesterday, tries to frame that
in the mindset of the original owner, that the original owner wants
to transfer the כפל kefel to the שומר shomer in order so
that he can get paid up the principal now, so it's not
a תקנה takana but it's trying to get into the psychology of
the owner. Because the גמרא gemara situated it in the psychology of
the owner and made it almost like implicitly the original owner is
agreeing to this, the גמרא gemara has a problem about the mechanism
through which this happens, because the גמרא gemara says how can you
transfer כפל? kefel? כפל kefel doesn't exist yet. How can you transfer
something that does not yet exist? If it was rabbinic, who knows,
you know we have more latitude, but if it's really seen as
an implicit transaction that occurred between the two parties, what was the
mechanism for transferring the כפל kefel or transferring the object? So that
was the גמרא's gemara's question. So let's pick up with the answer
to this. Top of we did one answer yesterday, we're going to
start again with it and then we'll see other answers. So three
lines from the top of ל"ד ע"א, Lamed Dalet Amud Alef, אמר
רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava, נעשה כאומר לו, na'aseh k'omer lo,
it's as if the owner is saying to him, because deep down
this is what the owner really wants to is thinking, or because
we as the rabbis want the owner to be saying this so
we're going to say the owner is saying this, that's the תקנה
takana approach to this, it's as if the owner is saying לכשתגנב
ותרצה ותשלמני lechisheganiv v'tirtzeh v'teshalmeni
if and when it gets stolen or robbed actually and you agree
and you agree to pay me then if it ever happens הרי
פרתי קנויה לך מעכשיו harei parati knuya lach mei-achshav
this cow I'm giving you now to watch as of this moment
it will be your cow in the eventuality that it gets burgled
and that you agree to pay for it. And you do pay?
Well we'll see in a minute whether it's to agree or whether
you actually pay for it.
Michael, we're going to see. Okay, so מתקיף לה רבי זירא. matkif
lah Rabbi Zeira. So anyway... That's his point, it becomes an implicit
condition of,
if the following thing happens in the future, then retroactively from the
time of giving over the cow it is yours as of now.
Okay, and that's what deep down we think he really is thinking,
or deep down we're going to assert that deep down he's thinking
that in order so that we can make this work. מתקיף לה
רבי זירא, Matkif lah Rabbi Zeira, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira challenged this.
אי הכי, Ei hachi, אפילו גיזותיה וולדותיה נמי. afilu gizeha vevaladeha nami.
If that's true that he really owned the cow when this happens
from the time that the cow was given to him to watch,
he should be entitled to keep any of the shearings, let's say
it's a sheep, or any of the babies of the cow. So
the owner gives me a, let's say a pregnant cow or a
sheep with wool, I go ahead and while I'm watching it or
whatever it's time for shearing the sheep so I shear it, or
the cow gives birth, and then it gets stolen. Now but the
wool and the sheep don't get and the calves don't get stolen,
only the sheep or the cow. So from a שומר's shomer perspective,
right, I give the owner back the wool or the calves, those
are still in my house, and I reimburse him for the sheep
or for the cow. But if let's say we do that, and
then but then it's a case of a גנב, ganav, and the
גנב ganav gets found. So now we're going to say, well, retroactively
now I owned it from the time that he gave it to
me. So actually if I owned it retroactively from the time I
started watching it, those shearings are mine, those calves are mine.
So I get to keep those, right, if I'm willing to pay,
forget even if you wait for כפל, kefel, right, as soon as
it was נגנב nignav and I say it was נגנב nignav and
I'm willing to pay, retroactively I should get the shearings and the
calves. So okay, so if that's true,
why would תניא tanya a ברייתא braita חוץ מגיזותיה וולדותיה, chutz migizeha
vevaladeha, that you know, you don't get the shearings and the babies?
אלא אמר רבי זירא, Ela amar Rabbi Zeira,
so here's the mechanism. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said, נעשה
כאומר לו, na'aseh ke'omer lo, it's like he says to him: חוץ
מגיזותיה וולדותיה, chutz migizeha vevaladeha, that okay, we have to throw that
in in the implicit condition. Retroactively you will own it from the
time that I am giving it to you, from this moment, except
for any shearings or babies or whatever, those are all mine, but
other than that it'll be yours. Okay, so obviously we're trying to
carve it out so you own it just enough to get כפל.
kefel. So הגמרא haGemara says, ומה פסקא, u'mah paska, and what makes
you sort of split it that way, that retroactively you'll own it
for those purposes but not for the כפל? kefel? You'll own it
for כפל kefel purposes but not for those purposes. So סתמא דמילתא,
stama d'milsa, שבחא דאתי מעלמא עביד איניש דאקנויי. shivcha d'asi me'alma avid
inish d'aknoiyi. No, because we can assume people are willing to give
in some type of external benefit like כפל kefel that's coming from
outside the animal. שבחא דמגופיה, shivcha d'migufah, benefit that comes from the
animal itself, לא עביד איניש דאקנויי, lo avid inish d'aknoiyi, they're not
willing to give. And therefore בקיצור, bekitzur, they, you know, so כפל,
kefel, which is who knows if it's going to happen, and it's
not a part of the animal itself, you want me to give
you you should own it for that so that you can get
כפל, kefel, go to town, but I'm not going to retroactively just
because you're willing to reimburse me make you own it for the
גיזות gizos and the ולדות, velados, something that comes from the animal
itself. So we carve out a very specific type of a condition
that will allow the guy to get the כפל kefel and nothing
else. That's one answer. Okay, now another answer is איכא דאמרי אמר
רבא, ika d'amri amar Rava, others say רבא Rava gave a different
answer.
נעשה כאומר לו, na'aseh ke'omer lo, it's like he said to
him: לכשתגנב ותרצה ותשלמני, lich'sheteiganav veseirtzeh ushalmeni, when if it gets robbed
and you desire and you pay me, סמוך לגניבתה קנויה לך, samuch
lignevasah kenuya lach, you'll own it a second before it gets stolen.
So therefore because I'm transferring ownership to you a second before it
gets stolen, sort of like a מתנת שכיב מרע, matnas shechiv mera,
you know, the whatever, some type of a gift that takes place
a second before the guy dies. So you'll own it a second
before it gets stolen and therefore any benefit that accrued to it
until that moment will be mine, the owner, but you'll get it
at that second and therefore the גנב ganav will have stolen it
from you and you'll be entitled to כפל. kefel. So הגמרא haGemara
says, מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, what would be a practical difference between
these two approaches? First of all, איכא בינייהו קושיית דרבי זירא. ika
beinaihu kushyas d'Rabbi Zeira. Number one, the second approach does not have
the challenge of the shearings and the babies, you know, it already
anticipated that problem and therefore you don't have to create this special
like, and we made a condition to exclude the shearings and the
babies. By transferring ownership to you a second before it gets stolen,
that sort of solves that problem. Okay, but is there a practical
difference between these two answers? So הגמרא haGemara says, yes. אי נמי
דקיימא באגם. Ei nami d'kaima b'agam. Let's say it gets stolen
not from Michael the שומר, shomer, not from Michael's property, it gets
stolen when it's grazing out in the swamp. So in that case
if it's grazing out in the swamp, even if I wanted to
transfer it to Michael at that moment, he's not holding on to
it, it's not on his property, there's no mechanism for him to
take possession of it. He can retroactively own it from the moment
I handed it to him two weeks ago, because then it was
in his hand, it was on his property, but he can't own
it the second before it got stolen. because there's no act of
taking possession at that second. So the problem with this answer, while
it's a more elegant answer, the problem with it is that it
would not cover cases when the thing was stolen not directly off
of Michael's property. Yes, Charlie.
Would we use this idea of אגם agam as the animal is
out somewhere and there's no way we can get... how can it
be stolen if it's out there?
No, obviously. What do you mean? It's accessible. I mean, it's true
that the גמרא Gemara sometimes talks about אגם agam as a way
that you, like we dealt with the אשישנא, ashishna, that you would
keep it out of the hands of בית דין, Beis Din, it
would be hard to find, but it doesn't mean that it's אבודה
ממנו ומכל אדם, avudah mimenu u-mikol adam, it just means that it's
a more of a secret location. But some smart גנב ganav was
able to find it there. So unless it's in like
a swamp, like it's in quicksand.
No, no, no. It just means it's not on Michael's property and
therefore there's no way for him to do a קנין. kinyan. Now
another interesting possibility which a different גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin discusses
is can you... why don't I just say Michael, if it gets
stolen then retroactively you will own it for the כפל kefel purposes
and nothing else, as of this minute? Meaning, not you'll own it
a hundred percent, but minus גיזות וולדות. gizos u-velados. No, you only
own it for the sake of its כפל. kefel. For all other
purposes under this earth, it is my cow, but for the question
of גניבה gneivah and for the questions of כפל, kefel, it's your
cow. Okay? Like, can you sort of split it like that? Or
do we say no, that כפל kefel results from a broader question
of ownership, you can't just own it for the purposes of כפל.
kefel. Anyway, that's another version that the גמרא Gemara in גיטין Gittin
has. Anyway, some type of implicit transferring of ownership when certain conditions
are met to allow him to own it in order that he
could get כפל, kefel, but the key also is that this is
not just saying this is a תקנה, takanah, this is rooting it
or claiming that that is the דעת da'as of the parties or
of the owner in order to... and that creates that mechanism that
then will allow the person to get כפל. kefel. Yes, Mike.
I'm trying to understand something. So let's say I just, you know,
give you whatever, this iPhone, right? I say, here you watch it
now and two weeks from now you'll own it, right? I can't
do that? You can. Okay, so what's the problem with the אגם
agam thing? I'm giving it to you now to watch... So okay,
so רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos discuss this. If you say you
will be קונה koneh two weeks from now just like that, then
at that moment when I'm קונה koneh two weeks from now, there
has to be some מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan present at that moment.
It has to be in my hand, it
has to be on my רשות. reshus. However, what תוספות Tosafos asks
and what you might be asking is why don't you say it's
קנויה לך knuyah lach מעכשיו me'achshav and two weeks from now? So
that's what תוספות Tosafos says. תוספות Tosafos says, if you look at
תוספות Tosafos of אי נמי דקאמר באגם, i nami d'ka'amar b'agam, תוספות
Tosafos says תימה, teima, לנימא נעשה כאומר לו לכשתגנב ותשלמני הרי פרתי
קנויה לך מעכשיו סמוך לגניבתה. leneima na'aseh k'omer lo le'kichshe'tignav ve-tishalmeni harei
parasi knuyah lach me'achshav samuch l'gneivasa. Like you situate it in two
times.
Retroactively as of now, finishing a minute before it's stolen. And because
you add the
"retroactively as of now," that is enough to obviate the need of
a new מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan a moment before it's stolen, because
it starts now, it finishes a minute before it's stolen. But because
it begins now, that's the only מעשה קנין ma'aseh kinyan you need.
So that's תוספות's Tosafos question. תוספות's Tosafos answer is that maybe even
in that case, because it begins as of now, you would be
entitled to the גיזות וולדות, gizos u-velados, so it wouldn't solve the
problem that we raised.
But תוספות Tosafos does ask that question. Okay, let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. שילם ולא רצה לישבע. Shilem ve-lo ratzah lishava.
Now we're going to deal with the conditions under which the person
is entitled to the כפל. kefel. So it says he pays and
he didn't want to take an oath. So when I was translating
before I said agreed to pay, the גמרא Gemara says pays, what
do you mean agree to? So that's the issue the גמרא Gemara
is going to ask. Let's take a look. אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan,
לא שילם שילם ממש. lo shilem shilem mamash. When it says in
the משנה Mishnah when you pay you're entitled to it, the כפל,
kefel, it doesn't mean you have to literally pay. אלא כיון שאמר
הריני משלם אף על פי שלא שילם. Ela kivan she-amar hareni meshalem
af al pi she-lo shilem. Once you agree to pay, even if
you haven't yet paid. Now we'll discuss in a little while that,
you know, the question that's not clear in the גמרא, Gemara, but
whether once you agree to pay, are you allowed to change your
mind? And is there a way that you're locked into that decision?
Maybe you would have to agree in front of עדים, eidim, you'd
have to agree in... no, no, no, but that's about a normal
sale. I'm talking about here that there's a sort of, it's a
case of a court case, right? You have two options in terms
of your responsibilities to me. Your option is pay or take an
oath. If you choose the pay option, are you allowed then to
change your mind and go for the oath option? And maybe it
would only be if you agreed in court or before witnesses or
whatever. So that's not clear yet, but it's certainly easier to understand
this statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you don't have to
pay, you just have to agree to pay, if you're locked in
to that decision, because then I know you're going to pay, so
even if you didn't yet get to go to the ATM or
whatever, but once that's going to be what's going to happen, fine,
you're entitled to the כפל kefel and then the גנב ganav shows
up before you got a chance to pay. Okay, if you're allowed
to take it back, okay, then first of all, any smart person
would say... Okay, I agree to pay, and then wait, wait, wait
till the last possible moment because maybe the גנב ganov will be
found, right? So okay, besides that you can sort of game the
system, but anyway, even putting that aside, what is it a benefit
of me that you agreed if you can retract? Unless something is...
no, we assume most of the time if a person's agreeing, eventually
they're going to do it. And again, I want to get that
person to agree, so we want to incentivize, you know, as much
as possible. But that sounds like a transaction, so it's not really
a transaction בעל פה. ba'al peh. There's no שטר, shtar, there's no
קנין. kinyan. Right, exactly. And it might even not be binding, which
is really what a tremendous חידוש chiddush of Rabbi Yochanan if it's
not binding. But that's what he says. You don't have to pay,
you just have to agree to pay. כיון שאמר הרי אני משלם
אף על פי שלא שילם. Keivan she'amar harei ani m'shalem af al
pi she'lo shilem. Okay now, let's see how the משנה Mishna bears
this out. תנן, T'nan, a משנה Mishna says: שילם ולא רצה לישבע.
shilem v'lo ratza lishava. If you pay and don't want to take
an oath, then you get the כפל. kefel. שילם אין, לא שילם
לא. Shilem in, lo shilem lo. Only if you paid, not if
you didn't pay. No, אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the
end of the משנה. Mishna. נשבע ולא רצה לשלם. Nishba v'lo ratza
lishalem. If he took an oath and he didn't want to pay.
טעמא דלא רצה. Ta'ama d'lo ratza. So the only reason is because
he didn't want to pay. Okay? הא רצה, Ha ratza, once you
wanted to pay, it doesn't say נשבע ולא שילם. nishba v'lo shilem.
It says נשבע ולא רצה לשלם. nishba v'lo ratza lishalem. He didn't
want to. If you wanted to, הא רצה אף על פי שלא
שילם. ha ratza af al pi she'lo shilem. You would presumably you'd
get it even if you didn't pay. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה.
Ela mei'ha leika l'mishma mina. From this משנה Mishna you cannot infer
it because you know it deals again with two extremes and not
with the excluded middle here. So we do not know, it's it's
ambiguous about the case of where you're not taking an oath, you're
willing to pay, but you haven't yet paid. Okay, by the way,
just which something that isn't discussed here but was discussed in a
different גמרא, Gemara, is the other thing that's vague about the משנה,
Mishna, talking about the two extremes, it says you paid and you
didn't take an oath. You took an oath and you didn't pay.
Let's say, or you want to pay, but for anyway, let's talk
about a case where you took an oath and then you changed
your mind and said you know what, I will pay you. Okay,
so how about that case? That's actually debated in you know in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, it's so where maybe one of our opinions:
well now you're agreeing to pay me, so now fine, because then
anything that can incentivize you to pay me all the more so.
You took an oath, you could have walked away and you're still
agreeing to pay me, of course now I'd be willing to give
you כפל. kefel. Others say no, part of the whole incentive here
is that we don't have to as as Rabbi Dov was saying,
we don't have to bring this case to court. You're making it
easy on me, you're just paying me right up front. The fact
that now we had to go to whole court and I had
to force you to take an oath and whatever and finally you
agreed to pay, that's too much effort for me. That's not a
case that you get כפל. kefel. Okay, so those are two cases
that are not clear in the משנה. Mishna. One a different גמרא
Gemara discusses, our משנה Mishna says you took you paid and you
didn't take an oath, you took an oath and you didn't pay.
Let's say you took an oath and now you are willing to
pay or now you did pay. What would be that story? That's
not being discussed here. What's being discussed here is the רצה לשלם.
ratza lishalem. Where it says he's paid and says he didn't want
to pay. What if you didn't pay yet but you agreed to
pay, you wanted to? And that's what Rabbi Yochanan is saying you're
entitled to the כפל, kefel, but that's not clear in the משנה.
Mishna. Yes. Is a check like a... is a check considered like
a payment, meaning it has to clear first? Well, that's a good
question. I mean... maybe he knows there... right away and then there's
a note that maybe may be backdated. That's a good question, I
don't know. Okay, yeah, if you say that שילם shilem as opposed
to רצה לשלם. ratza lishalem. It certainly is more in the sense
that you can't detract, I mean I guess once it cleared then
retroactively we saw it was a good check and there was no
way of backing out. Yeah, probably we would have to see I
mean it might depend on whether retroactively it cleared or not, you
know, whether it determined whether you wanted to or didn't want to,
you could always change your mind. He says he wants to, he
says fine, I'll pay. Yeah, right, he says it. Okay, but the
question is you know as I'm saying like what good is the
saying if you can retract? But it might be good. Once you
get people to say they will, under most cases they will do
it, and you know it is sort of moving things along. Okay,
but that's the גמרא's Gemara not making that clear whether he can
retract, but he does say that he'll pay. Okay, yeah. From the
משנה Mishna it sounds like the רישא Reisha and סיפא Seifa are
parallel. He did X and he didn't want to do Y, and
then the next one is he did Y and he didn't want
to do X. Right, they are symmetrical, but as the גמרא Gemara
says symmetrical does not mean that it covers all cases, all the
cases in the in the universe. But it's like in both of
them the didn't want is taking a back seat to the what
he actually did. I agree with you. You mean... understand, one case
it says he paid, the other case he says he took an
oath. Let's say he didn't pay and he didn't take an oath.
So what's the story? Which category does it fall into? And he's
even willing to pay. Right? So take out the לא רצה lo
ratza part, it's still not clear what you do about a case
that's neither A nor B, right? So that's always the problem. Symmetrically
it sounds nice. He swore, he paid and he didn't take an
oath, he took an oath and he didn't pay. It's a very
nice symmetrical way of saying it, but it does not cover, it's
not explicitly covering the entire universe of cases, which is what the
גמרא Gemara has to analyze. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara to me
it's not clear which one. I mean I guess to me since
the חידוש chiddush is that he gets כפל kefel and the first
thing it says is that he gets כפל kefel when he paid,
the more natural... And everything else, if you're not, don't satisfy the
first condition, pay, then everything else you don't get כפל. kefel. Right.
Okay, that's true. That's taking the first case as the defining case
as the A and everything else is not A. So even the
way the משנה mishna is structured is A you you get כפל,
kefel, B you don't, you want to read B as anything that's
not A. I understand that but again the גמרא Gemara is not
convinced. Okay so גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה מישמע מינה
תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Amreila leh mishmah minah, Tani k'vayei d'Rabbi Yochanan.
Now we taught like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that agreeing to pay
is enough. השוכר פרה מחבירו ונגנבה. HaSocher para mechavero venignava. So you
rented this is not a case about about שומר חנם. shomer chinam.
Okay here's a case where if it's נגנב nignav you actually have
to pay. So there's going to be other חידושים chiddushim we're going
to find out here. You rented a cow and it's stolen, ואמר
הלה הריני משלם ואיני נשבע. ve'amar halah harei ani m'shalem v'eini nishba.
I agree to pay, I'm not going to take an oath. Notice
you just say you're going to pay. Okay and ואחר כך נמצא
הגנב. v'acharchach nimtza haganav. And the גנב ganav is found, משלם תשלומי
כפל לשוכר. m'shalem tashlumei kefel lasocher. You pay it to the renter.
Okay that's explicit, you just agree to pay, you see even agreeing
is enough. By the way, the other thing that needs to be
mentioned here very importantly and parenthetically which the גמרא's Gemara going to
say sort of in a different way in a second, is that
here you're legally obligated to pay. So it's one thing to say
if I'm a שומר חנם shomer chinam and I agree to pay
even though legally I'm entitled to be exempt. My claim is that
it was stolen, according to my claim I'm legally exempt and nevertheless
I'm agreeing to pay so that's like one thing where we want
to incentivize people to pay even when they're not obligated. If I'm
a שוכר, socher, I'm legally obligated in a case of גניבה. g'neiva.
So because I'm doing the right thing and not lying under שבועה
shevua and right that's my alternative. My alternative is either pay like
I'm legally obligated to or take a false שבועה. shevua. So I
don't get a big pat on the back for not taking a
false שבועה. shevua. So you might think that that case I don't
get כפל kefel because I'm legally obligated to pay anyway. But no,
you know nevertheless you you were upfront, ready to do it, you
did not, you know take some, you didn't lie, you didn't take
a false שבועה, shevua, you didn't make us force to bring the
case to court and only agree after a lot of haggling. So
even in that case where all I'm doing is my legal obligation
and my only alternative is to take a false oath, even in
that case I'm entitled to get כפל kefel and even before I
paid, just as soon as I agreed to pay. Right. But that
doesn't answer the proof, I don't understand it, but the cases as
you just said are not parallel. In other words the שוכר socher
has to pay anyway. So when he's finally he's agreed to do
it, you know we know you're gonna pay, you know you know
you have to pay. Whereas the שומר חנם shomer chinam says I
don't have to pay anyway I'm agreeing to pay, you know what,
yeah that's pretty stupid, why am I agreeing to pay? So that's
interesting. I yeah, I hear that. I mean I my assumption was
was that it was a קל וחומר kal vachomer proof. Even a
שוכר socher who was doing what he was legally mandated and he
didn't even do it yet he only agreed to do it, even
there he gets כפל. kefel. But you're trying to read it a
little differently. Since he's legally obligated he really can't back out. Right?
But I don't know, he could go back and say and says
you know what actually I don't know my like it's you might
be right, it might be harder to back out, you could say
I reconsidered the circumstances and I realized it really wasn't אונס onus
or something like that. But you're right, he's like once he says
that he can he his options are more closed off, that didn't
occur to me. So on the one hand he's not doing anything
that we should give him a big יישר כח yashar koach for
and you know so you might expect more from him to actually
pay but you do make a good point that he also can't
back out as easily. Yes, Charlie? Does the שומר שוכר shomer socher
become the owner of the thing that he is guarding because it
seems like here the fact he's getting the כפל kefel at some
point he became the owner... Yeah, it's the same mechanism as we
said before, retroactively he owns it, whatever the mechanism is that we
said before. You said he's legally obligated to pay, the renter, right?
Right. But he could also swear and then not have to pay,
or not? He could swear falsely. He can't swear he can swear
falsely that it was an אונס, onus, but he cannot swear honestly
and not pay. If he swears falsely he's swearing what? That it's
stolen, he still has to pay? So if he swears it was
stolen he's got to pay. The only way he would get out
of it is if he swore that it was like armed bandits
and it was an אונס onus and it was you know out
of his control or whatever. So if but if but based on
what he's claiming, his only alternative would have been to swear falsely.
Okay. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says okay. אמר רב פפא. Amar
Rav Papa. So anyway we seem to be okay with that idea
at least for now that even just agreeing. אמר רב פפא. Amar
Rav Papa. And now we're gonna deal with variations on that issue
of agreeing. אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa. שומר חנם כיון דאמר
פשעתי מקני ליה כפילא. Shomer chinam kivan de'amar pashati makneh leh kefela.
If a שומר חנם shomer chinam says פשעתי, pashati, I was negligent,
okay, then he gets כפל kefel because again he could have said
I wasn't negligent and it was a גניבה. g'neiva. So there's another
case where he based on his own claim he's really just doing
the honest thing. But even he didn't say I'm gonna pay, meaning...
well, פשעתי pashati becomes a an admission of an agreement to pay,
but you're right, he didn't say get those words out. But by
admitting that he's פשעתי pashati he's basically agreeing to pay. Okay but
so it's really everybody, right. But again the חידוש chiddush here is
is that his payment is just according to what he's saying what
he's obligated to do anyway. and that's enough. Okay, ואיבעית אימא ve-ibayis
eima נעשה na'aseh בגניבה. bi-gneivah. Now the reason is is because he
could have made a claim, maybe it would have been a lie
based on what he's saying, but at least he could have if
he wanted to, you know, cheated his way out of it and
said it was נגנבה. nignevah. So to get him to be honest,
we're going to have him say that. שומר שכר, Shomer sachar, now
this is expanding on the חידוש chidush we said a minute ago.
כיון Keivan דאמר de-amar נגנבה, nignevah, once he admits that it was
robbed, מקנה makneh ליה leih כפלא. kifla. Again, so A, you don't
have to pay, you just have to admit it, and B, even
if it's only you're admitting to your legal obligation. Now here, if
it was stolen, what was his alternative? I mean, first of all,
rewarding him for just telling the truth. But even that, what else
could he have said? No, דאי de-ei בעי bei פטר pattar נפשיה
nafsheih בשבורה bi-shvurah ומתה, u-metah, he could have said yes, it's not
around because it fell off a cliff, okay, because he could have
he could have made up a story. So because you so in
order to get you just for doing the right thing and being
honest and not lie under oath, okay, if there was a way
you could have gotten out of it, we're going to incentivize you
to do the honest thing. Okay, and is this all בפנים bifnim
או o חוץ chutz מפנים? mi-pnim? We don't know yet. Okay, you're
right, but that's an important question. Now, okay, so so far we're
just expanding on what we said before. You don't have to pay,
you just have to agree, and you don't even have to agree
to do something beyond your legal obligation. You just have to be
honest. Okay, as long as you're being honest and you're not taking
the option of lying under oath and and that's enough to get
you כפל. kefel. שואל Shoel שאמר she-amar הריני hareini משלם, meshallem, the
one exception is if a borrower says I'm going to pay, לא
lo מקנה makneh ליה leih כפלא, kifla, the owner does not transfer
כפל kefel in that case. What why do they need to incentivize
the שואל? shoel? What option does the שואל shoel have of getting
out? במאי Be-mai הוה havah ליה leih למיפטר le-miptar נפשיה? nafsheih? What
was the only way he could have exempted himself? במתה Bi-metah מחמת
machamat מלאכה. melachah. There's one scenario that the שואל shoel is exempt.
If lightning strikes the cow, the שואל shoel is liable. If the
cow has a heart attack, the שואל shoel is liable. If a
lion attacks the cow, the שואל shoel is liable. The one case
the שואל shoel is not liable is if the cow dies in
the normal course of use. Because basically you say to the guy,
like, I borrowed it to use it, so you implicitly okayed you
accepted implicitly the risk. Like, you say I'm going to use it
to plow my field. In the course of plowing my field it
drops dead, okay, as a result of plowing my field it's so
funny, like if it just drops dead of cancer, then I'd have
to pay you. But if it dropped dead out of the normal
exertion involved in plowing the field, then I don't have to pay
you because you understood that's how I was going to use it
and you were allowing me to use it. Okay, so now, of
course, if there was any misuse of it, right? If I'm borrowing
your iPhone and I'm being my normal klutzy self and it slips
out of my hand and it cracks the screen, that's not מתה
metah מחמת machamat מלאכה, melachah, okay? That's my own negligence or whatever.
Okay? But if I was doing nothing but anyway, but if it
was a normal type of if it was a natural thing that
resulted from the use, then you as the lender were implicitly giving
me the right to use it and accepting that risk. Yeah. Why
so אונס ones doesn't apply to a שואל, shoel, it died of
cancer. Correct. אונס Ones does not apply to a שואל. shoel. Because
you're taking it, you get all the benefit, you are fully liable.
Yeah, that's the הלכה halacha בשואל. be-shoel. ובעליו u-be'alav עמו imo is
another exception. Okay? But so anyway, so the point here is that
if I'm a שואל shoel and I agree to pay, right, why
is it necessary to incentivize me to agree to pay? To get
to stop me from lying that it was מתה metah מחמת machamat
מלאכה. melachah. Okay, well why not? That's a good incentive. Stop me
from making up that lie. The גמרא Gemara says, no, that's not
enough to incentivize you that you shouldn't make that lie. Why? דאי
de-ei בעי bei פטר pattar נפשיה nafsheih במתה bi-metah מחמת machamat מלאכה,
melachah, מתה metah מחמת machamat מלאכה melachah לא lo שכיח. shchi'ach. Because
it's not so common that something will die מחמת machamat מלאכה, melachah,
a normal cow will drop dead out of normal use or something
of that nature, right, or a hammer will break out of normal
use. I mean, I don't know, it's not so I mean who
knows? I you know, it's not so crazy things do break when
you use them. You sit on a couch, it breaks, or whatever.
Anyway, but the גמרא Gemara says that we don't have to create
an incentive. People are going to the likelihood that somebody will make
that claim, be prepared to make that claim when it's not true,
is very small. So therefore we don't have to incentivize somebody not
to make that type of a lie. Okay, but the other things
we do need to incentivize them. Okay, that's one explanation. But the
big so besides the חידוש chidush that שואל shoel isn't included is
the חידוש chidush that these other things are, even though they're not
paying, they're just agreeing, and even though the only thing that you're
doing, the wonderful thing you the שומר, shomer, the שוכר socher are
doing is you're not lying under oath. Nevertheless, you're entitled to כפל.
kefel. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, איכא ika דאמרי de-amri
אמר amar רב פפא, Rav Pappa שואל נמי. shoel nami, You know
what? Even a שואל shoel we'll give him כפל. kefel. Let's just
get everybody the owner reimbursed, doesn't really matter, you know. So we
just want to incentivize everything and get things back to normal. שואל
shoel נמי, nami. כיון שאמר הריני משלם, keivan she'amar hareni meshalem, once
he agrees to pay, מקני ליה כפילא, makni leh kefila, the owner's
willing to transfer כפל. kefel. דבעי פטור נסי במתה מחמת מלאכה. d'ba'ei
pator nasei b'meta machamat melacha. Yeah, because even a שואל shoel could
have made some other claim, so you just want to encourage everybody
to just not consider their other possible claims and just pay up
as quickly as possible. All right, and all this when he when
it's known that it hasn't, let's say, been stolen or whatever it
is, I mean, let's say like a גנב, ganav, like I don't
have any information that like עדים המשיחין ובאים edim hameshichin v'bo'im that
oh yeah there was a גנב ganav out there. I don't know
any of that, right? Because if you do know that then I
wouldn't want to be מקנה makne the כפל kefel necessarily. Oh, you
mean if I know the owner was stolen I know it's more
likely that that כפל kefel is a possibility. Yes, something like you
know. No, no, we're not excluding those cases. Even if it's I
mean I guess some of these possibilities though you're right make it
clear that it's not clearly clear that it was נגנב. nignav. But
even in the case where it was like clear where it was
נגנב, nignav, we're not excluding that as cases where we assume I'm
giving כפל. kefel. Okay, I mean I guess another question would be
you see the גנב ganav is about to be captured and then
that would be a more parallel case, not just you know it
was נגנב. nignav. Okay, that would be an interesting case when the
גנב ganav is like about to be captured. Okay, yeah right, exactly,
exactly. Okay, so אמר ליה רב זביד, amar leh Rav Zvid, so
הכי אמר אביי, hachi amar Abaye, so these two answers about רב
פפא Rav Pappa about a שואל, shoel, about whether a שואל shoel
also gets כפל kefel when he agrees to pay. So זביד Zvid
says here's what אביי Abaye said, שואל עד שישלם. shoel ad sheyeshalem.
שואל shoel it's true will get כפל kefel but he's the one
guy we make actually have to pay and not just say he
will, because a שואל shoel is doing a much smaller טובה tova
to the owners because the שואל's shoel options of getting out of
it are much smaller. Okay, him we're going to want him to
actually really make it easier on the owner and actually pay up
and not just say he's going to pay up. Okay, מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama up front, up front. What's the reason? הואיל וכל הנאה
שלו ho'il v'chol hana'ah shelo and now he reframes, I framed it
as a continuation of רב Rav פפא Pappa, because because his options
of getting out of it are smaller. But רב זביד Rav Zvid
frames it here in a different way. הואיל וכל הנאה שלו, ho'il
v'chol hana'ah shelo, since he got all the benefit of the initial
transaction, the owner is not so predisposed to give him כפל. kefel.
Doesn't feel so grateful to him. Now this is a new consideration
which we sort of saw a little bit at the very beginning
of the פרק perek yesterday which is not just my very rational
practical consideration I'm going to incentivize him to pay up so that
and give him כפל kefel so that I get reimbursed as quickly
as possible. It's also a feeling like the guy did me a
favor. He was watching my object. The גמרא Gemara yesterday discussed the
idea it was a sheep, he had to take it out grazing
every single day. I feel a little bit grateful to him and
not only that, he's even saying he's going to pay me when
he had other options. I'm going to let him keep the כפל
kefel just in case in case a גנב ganav is actually found.
And so he did in the end this little extra bonus right
if it's what do you call it if a גנב ganav is
actually found. And a שואל shoel he did me no favors. I
gave him the favor. So I did him all the favor. I
lent him my thing. I didn't even get paid for it, right?
It was all a completely in a שוכר socher it was a
two-sided thing. I did him a favor but he paid me for
it or whatever. This was a completely one-sided transaction. In that type
of a case, I'm not so predisposed to let him get the
כפל. kefel. If he actually goes and pays me cash up front
right now and I put it back, that case yes, but just
promising I'm more hesitant to do it. So it makes it a
little bit more about the interpersonal relationship and not just a clear
business type of decision. Now תוספות Tosafot says the difference between those
two approaches about the שואל, shoel, whether it's because how much how
many options does he have anyway versus how much do I feel
do I feel positively inclined towards him is let's say I made
a special stipulation with the שואל. shoel. Michael asks to borrow my
rake and Michael said I will I will Dov I want to
borrow your rake and I want you to agree that I'm not
going to be liable for גניבה ואבידה. gneivah v'aveida. I'm only going
to be liable if it's negligence. Okay, so he so he got
me not only to lend him a rake but also to give
him a big a big pass on a lot of things. I
said fine whatever only if you're negligent will you be liable. Okay,
and then it breaks or something happens it gets stolen. Okay, so
in that case if the whole reason we're treating שואל shoel different
is because he doesn't have any other options, serious options, in this
case he has other options, he could just claim he wasn't negligent,
right? So that would be so in that so if your approach
was the other options that a שואל shoel had, then in this
case where he does have other options he would get כפל kefel
even by just agreeing to pay. Whereas if your approach was by
אביי Abaye about the I was so I was so I was
so good to him, I'm not so inclined to give him the
כפל, kefel, then I was even nicer to him in this case.
right? So that would be so that would be like a נפקא
מינא *nafka mina* between these two approaches. Okay so רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* says so first of all right רב פפא *Rav Pappa* says
he's not sure if the שואל shoel. *shoel* you know by if
the שואל shoel *shoel* claims that he gets כפל kefel, *kefel* or
not because he really doesn't have any other options and אביי *Abaye*
says he will get it but only if he pays and if
the reason to be more hesitant by the שואל shoel *shoel* is
not the question of the options available to him but is because
he didn't do any favors to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit, *baal
habayis*. All right now let's see where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes
with this. Does he disagree with אביי *Abaye*? Well that's not clear
when רב פפא *Rav Pappa* in רב פפא *Rav Pappa*'s first לשון
*lashon* where רב פפא *Rav Pappa* says the שואל shoel *shoel* doesn't
get כפל kefel *kefel* would רב פפא *Rav Pappa* change his opinion
if the שואל *shoel* actually paid and is רב פפא *Rav Pappa*
just talking about if the שואל *shoel* agrees to pay? We don't
know. That's not clear. Right. So let's see where the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* goes. Okay so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. תני
כוותיה דרב זביד *tani kevasei deRav Zvid* we taught like רב זביד
*Rav Zvid*. השואל פרה מחברו ונגנבה *hashoel parah mechaveiro venignevah* והקדים השואל
ושילם *vehikdim hashoel veshillem* and the שואל *shoel* stepped forward and paid
ואחר כך נמצא הגנב *veachar kach nimtza haganav* and then the גנב
ganav *ganav* was found משלם תשלומי כפל kefel. לשואל *meshallem tashlumei kefel
lashoel*. He gets כפל kefel, *kefel*. So that's completely consistent. It says
A he had to step forward and pay. He actually paid. He
didn't just say. He did pay. And then because he actually paid
only then and presumably only then he gets כפל kefel *kefel*. That's
very consistent with רב זביד *Rav Zvid*. The שואל *shoel* will get
it but only if he actually paid. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says now וללישנא קמא דרב פפא ודאי לא הוי תיובתא *ulelishna kama
deRav Pappa vadai lo havi tiyuvta*. Now the first approach of רב
פפא *Rav Pappa* that רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said look he doesn't
really have any other options so by saying he's going to get
he'll pay he doesn't get כפל kefel. *kefel* as a שואל *shoel*.
This ברייתא *braisa* is not necessarily a contradiction because רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* was only talking about saying you're going to get you're going
to pay. You don't get כפל kefel? *kefel* as a שואל *shoel*.
He might be prepared to say that actually paying a שואל *shoel*
will get כפל kefel *kefel*. He might agree with אביי *Abaye*. רב
פפא *Rav Pappa* was saying promising to pay is not enough for
a שואל *shoel* but actually paying might be enough. Okay אלא ללישנא
בתרא לימא תיהוי תיובתא *ela lelishna basra leima tehavi tiyuvta*. But the
second language of רב פפא *Rav Pappa* רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said
even a שואל *shoel*'s promise to pay gets him כפל kefel *kefel*.
So this ברייתא *braisa* said no only when a שואל *shoel* actually
pays. All right so you got it? We have basically right with
a שואל *shoel* we've got we've got we've got the idea that
promising to pay is not enough but actually paying does get you
כפל kefel. *kefel*. That's what רב זביד *Rav Zvid* says. That could
be implicit in the first approach of רב פפא *Rav Pappa* you
have to actually pay and that's what this ברייתא *braisa* says. But
then you have the second approach of רב פפא *Rav Pappa* that
even a שואל *shoel* just promising is enough. So this ברייתא *braisa*
seems to contradict it. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב פפא *leima tehavi tiyuvta
deRav Pappa*? אמר לך רב פפא *amar lach Rav Pappa* רב פפא
*Rav Pappa* will say to you מי עלימא ממתניתין *mi alima mimisnisin*?
No this ברייתא *braisa* is no different than our משנה Mishna *mishna*.
דקתני שילם *dekatani shillem* our משנה Mishna. *mishna* says pay you get
כפל kefel. *kefel*. ואוקימנא באמר *veokimna beamar* we said pay doesn't really
mean pay it means promising to pay. הכא נמי באמר *hacha nami
beamar* here too the ברייתא *braisa* when it says if a שואל
*shoel* pays it means promising to pay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says right מי דמי *mi dami*? How can you compare them? התם
לא קתני הקדים *hasam lo katani hikdim*. There the משנה Mishna. *mishna*
doesn't say he stepped forward or he jumped forward and paid. הכא
קתני הקדים *hacha katani hikdim* he jumped forward so it sounds like
he actually paid. So the גמרא Gemara... *Gemara* says no מאי mai?
הקדים הקדים ואמר *mai hikdim hikdim veamar*. No it means he jumped
forward and he agreed to pay. It still doesn't mean he paid.
Wait a minute. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says הא ניחא תני גבי
שוכר *ha nicha tani gabi socher*. Wait a minute. We taught another
ברייתא *braisa* earlier by by the renter and by the renter it
says ואמר *veamar*. It says when the שוכר *socher* says he'll pay
he gets כפל kefel. *kefel*. Remember that was a ברייתא *braisa* we
quoted earlier to support the whole idea that promising is enough. Okay
וגבי שואל הקדים *vegabi shoel hikdim*. By the שואל *shoel* it says
הקדים ושילם *hikdim veshillem*. By the שוכר *socher* it says אמר *amar*
you know and he gets כפל kefel. *kefel* and by the שואל
*shoel* it says and he stepped forward and paid he gets כפל
kefel? *kefel*. So it seems like it's exactly contrasting that. A שוכר
*socher* it's enough to promise and a שואל *shoel* you have to
pay. שמע מינה דוקא קתני *shma mina davka katani*. You see by
the שואל *shoel* it means like it says it means that you
actually paid contrasting to the שוכר *socher* that it's enough to promise
to pay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מידי גבי הדדי קתני
*midi gabi hadadi katani*? Who says these ברייתות baraitot, *braisos* are in
the same context? Who says that they're you know one you know
if they were taught right side by side it would say שוכר
שאמר הריני משלם *socher sheamar hareini meshallem* gets כפל kefel, *kefel* שואל
הקדים ושילם *shoel hikdim veshillem* gets כפל kefel *kefel*. Clearly it's contrasting
and saying there are different criteria but maybe they're coming from different
collections of ברייתות baraitot *braisos* and you know they're not talking to
one another. The one of the שואל *shoel* is just לאו דוקא
*lav davka*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so מידי גבי הדדי
קתני *midi gabi hadadi katani*? No. So שיילינהו לתנאי דבי רבי חייא
Rabbi Hiyya ודבי רבי אושעיא *shayilinhu letannai devei Rabbi Chiyya vedevei Rabbi
Oshaya*. So we asked the תנאים *tannaim* the people who repeat the
ברייתות baraitot *braisos* who have the ברייתות baraitot *braisos* memorized in the
house of רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiyya* and רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*. They
were the ones that sort of organized the ברייתות baraitot. *braisos* and
particularly the תוספתא Tosefta, *Tosefta*. And they we said to them do
these come from the same collection of ברייתות *braisos* or not? Okay?
So that's so we actually did a little textual you know research.
Okay? ואמרי גבי הדדי תניא *veamri gabi hadadi tanya*. And they said
yes these were actually taught side by side. Okay? It says השוכר
שאמר *hasocher sheamar* and it says השואל הקדים ושילם *hashoel hikdim veshillem*.
Clearly, it means that a שואל actually has to pay. Very interesting.
It's also interesting that it means that when they learned ברייתות, they
learned them more atomically, like or atomistically. Is that the word, atomistically?
Meaning they learned them as individual units and they didn't necessarily learn
them in full context. And then they had to go back to
the people who actually were the repositories of the knowledge and say,
could you tell us the fuller context of all the ברייתות that
were taught in this context? So anyway, so where are we? We
are about the idea that the משנה says pay, but the גמרא
Gemara. has said no, you don't have to pay, it's just promising
to pay is enough. A, promising to pay is enough. B, it's
enough even by somebody who really is liable according to his own
admission and his only alternative would have been to lie under oath.
Even for that type of a person, even he gets כפל, kefel
and he gets כפל kefel even by promising to pay. And the
only exception is the שואל. Since the שואל has very few alternatives,
or alternatively, since the שואל did no favors to the בעל הבית,
he will only get it when he actually pays. Okay, but even
he will get it when he's just doing the honest thing, right?
So it's not even that you did more than you were obligated,
you just did the honest thing, you didn't lie, or whatever, and
in those cases, promising it to do it or actually doing it
gets you כפל. kefel Okay, so now, yes? So, about this, the
way the ברייתות are taught, there are... there's all the משניות, mishnayot,
and then there's the collection we have today called the תוספתא, Tosefta,
right, some of which are in the בבלי Bavli or the ירושלמי,
Yerushalmi, and many of which... right, but there's a lot of ברייתות
that aren't in the תוספתא, Tosefta right. So how do we know
how they managed to get in the תוספתא Tosefta? or not in
the תוספתא? Tosefta, Well, there was an editing process of the תוספתא,
Tosefta. like there was of the משנה. That was the process of,
you know, רבי חייא edited the תוספתא. Tosefta And then there was
other stuff that didn't make it in the תוספתא or in the
משנה. Those were just external ברייתות. And some of them continued to
float around and remembered and taught, and some I'm sure have been
lost. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. Now,
פשיטא אמר איני משלם וחזר ואמר הריני משלם. pishita amar eini meshallem
vehazar ve'amar hareni meshallem. A person first says, I'm not going to
pay, I'm going to take an oath, and then he says, I'm
going to pay. So finally he agreed. Now the חידוש, chiddush, now
it's not so פשיטא pishita because you could have said that you
get only the bonus if you make everything simple from the beginning,
right? If you've been yanking me around for the last two weeks
saying you're going to take an oath and finally you agree to
pay, right, and maybe I even had to שלעפ shlep you to
court before you agreed to pay, maybe you don't get כפל, kefel.
maybe that's not enough of an incentive. But the גמרא Gemara. says
that's obvious. If at the end of the day you agree to
pay, you get כפל kefel, even if you've been resisting it for,
you know, until now. אלא אמר הריני משלם וחזר ואמר איני משלם.
ela amar hareni meshallem vehazar ve'amar eini meshallem. And here's where it
sounds like you have the right to retract. First you agreed to
pay, and our חידוש chiddush was agreeing is enough to give you
כפל. kefel. And then you say, I'm not going to pay. מאי?
mai? Okay, now what do you mean מאי? mai? Now you said
you're not going to pay, and now the גנב ganav is found.
Why should you get כפל? You're not doing anything for me now.
No, because maybe we don't take what you're saying seriously. מי אמרינן
מהדר קהדר ביה? mi amrinan mahadar kahadar beih? You are retracting yourself,
you know, reversing yourself, and therefore you're no longer promising it, and
therefore you don't get כפל if the גנב is found. או דילמא
במילתיה קאי? o dilma bemilteih ka'ei? No, really you are going to
pay me. ודחויי הוא דקמדחי ליה. vedichuyei hu dekamidchei leih. You're just
pushing me off. We've seen this before like when you owe me
money and you basically say, no, I don't owe you money because
you don't have the money on you. So yes, you are eventually
going to pay me, but you're saying, you know, I come to
you, I say, Michael, you said you were going to pay me,
pay up. You know what? I've been thinking about it again, I'm
not so sure I'm going to pay you. I think I'm actually
going to take a שבועה. shvua. So he'd rather say that than
say he's hard up for money and he doesn't have the cash
to pay me right now. So he keeps on, so he really
does want to pay me, but he just keeps on, you know,
saying those things because he's not ready to pay me just yet.
Okay, now the point is that even if that were true, maybe
he's not entitled to כפל for giving me such a hard time.
So the interesting thing is the גמרא Gemara, doesn't seem to care
right now about the hard time Michael's giving me. He was saying
he wasn't going to pay me for a whole month, finally he
agrees to pay me. Once he agrees, he's entitled to כפל. So
here too, if he's still planning on paying me even if he's
giving me a hard time and claiming he's not, he's still entitled
to כפל. The only possible question is maybe he really has retracted.
And if he's really retracted, then he's not entitled to כפל. So
it sounds like he's entitled to retract. That makes it so much
more בחידוש bechiddush of what we said earlier, that just saying you're
going to pay even though you retain the right to retract it
is still enough to give you כפל. Yes? And in terms of
the שואל paying, I believe the way it works is that you
have to pay the whole thing, right? You can't, like, pay in
installments, right? There's no such thing. No, I assume you could pay
in installments, like you could pay a חוב chov up in installments.
I don't know why you can't pay this in installments. Unless the
שומרין, shomrim, like even if I started paying. So the גמרא is
going to get to that. Let's read the next question that the
גמרא... Okay, by the way though, I just want to pause for
a moment because again I do think is... It’s so interesting, can
you retract, and if you can retract, how good was your promise?
Why was your promise so important to begin with? So תוספות Tosafos
actually goes against the simple sense of the גמרא, which sounds like
you actually are able to retract. And if you look at the
end of this תוספות וחזר, Tosafos Ve’chazar, תוספות Tosafos says like this:
he says, והכא, Vehacha, you see the line that starts with the
word גמר? Gamar? It is about ten lines before the תוספות Tosafos
is over, the תוספות וחזר. Tosafos Ve’chazar. The line starts with the
word גמר. Gamar. תוספות Tosafos says like this: והכא דקאמר מהדר קהדר
ביה לא שיכול לחזור, Vehacha dekamar mehadar kahadar bei lo sheyuchal lachzor,
it's not that he really can go back, אלא רוצה הוא לחזור,
ela rotzeh hu lachzor, he wants to go back. If he were
able to, he would go back. אף על פי שאינו יכול. Af
al pi sheino yachol. So then why does he not get כפל?
Once he's bound by it, what do I care if he's just
pushing me off and still wants to, or he really wants to
not? Nevertheless, he's going to be obligated. Even as although he says,
ולא מקני ליה, vlo makni lei, he says, ואינו רוצה אלא לחזור
הוא אף על פי שאינו יכול ולא מקני ליה כפלא משום דאתי
לבי דינא כאמרה בסמוך. veino rotzeh ela lachzor hu af al pi
sheino yachol vlo makni lei kefela mishum daati lvei dina kamra besamuch.
So now we get to the fact, so תוספות Tosafos wants to
read it that actually he's not able to retract, which in one
way is good, it means that when he promises to pay, it
more explains why he's entitled to כפל, because he really is bound
by that statement. So the fact that the גמרא here speaks about,
well, what if he now is trying to retract, it really means
he's not able to, but he's trying. And is the fact that
he's trying and going to make my life harder and going to
make me have to force him in בית דין beis din to
hold by his original statement, therefore even though he is bound by
it, he loses his right to כפל because of his attempt to
get out of it. Okay? Yeah, so anyway, so that's an interesting
question here, which gets to the core question that since we're saying
the promising is enough, if promising is enough and are you bound
by your promise or are you not bound by your promise? The
simple sense of the גמרא is that you're not bound by your
promise, which makes the idea that promising gives you כפל an even
bigger חידוש. chiddush. Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Okay. Okay.
Now the גמרא says like this: אמר הריני משלם ומת. Amar hareini
meshallem umet. He says he's going to pay and then he dies.
Right? We have all these interesting questions because we said it's not
about actually paying. If it was all about actually paying, we could
do away with this whole דף daf of גמרא. Then there's no
question, did you pay or did you not pay? But because it's
about saying, you said and then you changed your mind. You said
and then this happened. You said and then that happened. Okay? So
the guy said he was going to pay and then he dropped
dead. אמר הריני משלם ומת. Amar hareini meshallem umet. ואמרו בניו אין
אנו משלמים, Vamru banav ein anu meshallmim, and then the kids say,
you know what? We're not going to pay. Okay, now of course
I don't know how they can not pay, how can they take
an oath about what happened since they don't know what happened? Maybe
they say we're going to find witnesses to prove what happened. Anyway,
מאי? mai? What do we say? מי אמרינן מהדר קהדרה ביהו? Mi
amrinan mehadar kahadra beihu? They are reversing the earlier decision? או דילמא
מילתא דאבון קיימינא? O dilma milta deavun kaimina? No, they're just saying
that they really are planning on paying, ודחויי הוא דקא דחיי ליה,
udechuyei hu deka dachyei lei, they're just pushing the guy off for
the time being. שילמו בנים Shillmu banim now, let's say forget the
case of אמרו, amru, they actually did pay. The שומר shomer died,
he said nothing, and the kids paid. Okay? So that should be
a straightforward case, the guy got his money back. Now, מאי? mai?
מצי אמרי להו כי אקני כפלא לאבוך דעביד לי נייחא רוחא. Matzei
amri lehu ki akni kefela lavucha david li naichas ruach. No, I
was willing to transfer כפל to your father, he did a favor
for me, he watched the object. לדידכו, Ledichu, you never did a
favor for me. So even though it's in my business interest from
the rational incentive perspective, I should be just as willing to give
the כפל to the kids if I'm going to get reimbursed, right?
This gets back to the point we said before, it's not all
about being rational and business-minded. All right? Part of it might be
because we're situating this in the דעת daas of the owner, we're
not just making this a תקנה. takkanah. So then we're saying an
important factor might be how grateful he is to the other person.
So therefore even though he has just as, if not maybe even
a stronger reason to be willing to pay the kids... you know,
now it's the kids, it's going to get caught up in the
court system even longer, okay? Nevertheless, even if there's just as good
or better business reason, since he doesn't have any gratitude towards the
kids, so maybe he's actually not going to give them the כפל.
So even if they do pay, I mean, isn't it maybe more
that they want to... I understand. That's the חידוש chiddush of the
גמרא, which really shows that it's not all about a business consideration.
I understand. Okay, it's not... anyway, מאי? mai? מצי אמר ליה כי
אקני כפלא לאבוך... Matzei amar lei ki akni kefela lavucha... או דילמא
לא שנא? o dilma lo shena? Or maybe it doesn't matter. שילמו
לבנים, Shillmu livanim, מאי? mai? Let's say the owner dies and the
שומר shomer is willing to pay the owner's kids, or actually pays
the owner's kids. So again, you would think all the more reason
to give him כפל, right? It's going to be so much harder,
we don't really know our father's business dealings, are we really going
to be able to recoup this loss? And then he just comes
straightforward and he pays and he makes my life so easy. Okay?
So from a business perspective, you should totally give him כפל. But
again, we're introducing this question about interpersonal. מאי? מצי אמר ליה כי
אקני... לדידן לא יהבינן כפילא *l'didon lo yahavinan kefela*. Our father would
have been willing to give you כפל *kefel* because you did a
favor to him, אבל אנן *aval anan* לדידן לא *l'didon lo*, you
never did any favor to us, says the heirs of the owner.
או דילמא לא שנא *O dilma lo shno*, or shouldn't matter? Who
cares about favors? They're getting their money back. שמע בנים לבנים מאי
*Shamu banim libanim mai*? Let's say both the owner and the borrower
died, and the heirs of the שומר *shomer* paid the heirs of
the owner. So there you again you should say and like you
know maybe that case like nobody did anybody, nobody who's alive did
any favor to anybody here. Nevertheless it's an you know maybe is
it a strictly business consideration or is it this question of who
did a favor to whom? שילם מחצה מאי *Shileim mechtzah mai*? That's
Michael's question. You made installments. You paid part. So do we say
that since you didn't pay all, now of course that's a funny
question because because how you if it's שילם מחצה *shileim mechtzah* presumably
you're agreeing to pay all and אמר *amar* should be enough. So
exactly what the scenario is, so רש"י *Rashi* says מתחילה אמר הריני
משלם מחצה ולא יותר *mitchila amar hareini m'shaleim mechtzah v'lo yoter*. So
right? Since אמר *amar* is enough, שילם *shileim*, so we have to
get a case that not only you only paid but you only
said you'd pay that. If you say look I was a שומר
חינם *shomer chinam* I'm exempt, it was נגנב *nignav*, I really am
exempt, but you know what let's call it a let's split it,
I'll pay half. Okay I so you couldn't agree to pay half
if you're really liable to pay the full but you could agree
to pay half if you're doing more than is necessary. What would
be the story there? שאל שתי פרות ושילם אחת מהן מאי *Sha'al
shtei parot v'shileim achat meihen mai*? Now it's interesting, we're going to
a שואל *sho'el*, right, because a שואל *sho'el* we said before has
to actually pay, not just promise to pay. So you borrowed two
cows and you paid full for one of them and the other
you're saying that I think I might make a שבועה *shvu'ah* for.
Do we treat those as two separate transactions? So the one you
paid for, you paid in full and therefore you get כפל *kefel*
if that turns out to be a גניבה *gneivah*? Or do we
say we look at it as one transaction and you didn't pay
for the whole thing and you don't get כפל *kefel*? שמע שותפין
ושילם לאחד מהן מאי *Shamu shutafin v'shileim l'echad meihen mai*? Or you
borrowed from partners and you paid one partner for his half. So
that partner you paid his full share, but you didn't pay for
the full object that you borrowed. Is that considered that at least
if גנב *ganav* gets found you get at least half כפל *kefel*
for the half you paid for? שותפין ששאלו ושילם אחד מהן מאי
*Shutafin she'sha'alu v'shileim echad meihen mai*? Now two partners borrowed and one
of the borrowers paid his half. So his obligation he paid in
full. Should he get כפל *kefel* for the part that he paid,
or should we say the object wasn't fully paid for? שמע מן
האשה ושילם לבעלה מאי *Shamu min ha'ishah v'shileim l'ba'alah mai*? Or you
borrowed from a woman and you paid her husband. או אשה ששאלה
ושילם בעלה מאי *O ishah she'sha'alah v'shileim ba'alah mai*? Or woman who
borrowed and her husband paid on her behalf. Is that like the
person herself paid or was paid? And there's a case where they
don't have that you know so there's whole debate of רש"י *Rashi*
and תוספות *Tosafot*, what's exactly the scenario of the woman and the
husband? Is it that the woman was it was an object that
was owned מן נכסי מלוג *min nikhsei melog*, the principal was owned
by the woman and the פירות *peirot* were owned by the husband?
So it's a question who's really seen of as the owner. It's
all interesting debate of רש"י *Rashi* תוספות *Tosafot* exactly what the scenario
is, but anyway the גמרא *Gemara* says תיקו *teiku*. On all of
these the גמרא *Gemara* says yeah those are all fascinating questions we
don't know. Okay, let's just try to get a little bit to
the next topic. אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav Huna*, says רב הונא
*Rav Huna*, משביעינן ליה שבועה שאינה ברשותו *mashbinan lei shvu'ah she'einah birshuto*.
So now we move beyond the כפל *kefel*. Let's take a deep
breath for a moment and get beyond all this כפל *kefel* and
שילם *shileim* and promising to pay. The guy says Michael, where's my
object? My beautiful new iPhone that I lent or I asked you
to watch it for you while I was going out swimming or
something, give it back to me. So Michael says tough, terrible thing
happened, it got lost, but don't worry I will pay you. Even
though I'm really exempt, it wasn't negligent, it was stolen, I'm going
to pay you. Great! So we have all these consequences of כפל
*kefel*. But comes רב הונא *Rav Huna* and says forget about that.
Maybe Michael just really wanted my iPhone and maybe he's saying that
it got lost and is agreeing to pay and that way he
gets out of taking any oath because right he doesn't have to
take an oath. But maybe he's really just doing this a way
to get my iPhone. So comes along רב הונא *Rav Huna* and
רב הונא *Rav Huna* says משביעינן ליה שבועה שאינה ברשותו *mashbinan lei
shvu'ah she'einah birshuto*. You thought Michael you would be able to pay
and not have to take a שבועה *shvu'ah*? You still have to
take a שבועה *shvu'ah* that you're not still holding onto it. That
even if you're going to agree to pay and you would think
that a big incentive to pay is that you don't have to
take a שבועה *shvu'ah*, says רב הונא *Rav Huna* you have to
take a שבועה *shvu'ah* that you're not really just holding onto it
yourself. I know מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama* what's the reason? חיישינן שמא
עיניו נתן בה *chashinan shema einav natan bah*, maybe he's not being
such a big צדיק *tzaddik*, maybe he's really just wants to keep
it to himself and is therefore claiming that something happened and he's
paying as a way to keep it. So we're going to now
see how does that work because all along we assumed the whole
point here was that there wasn't going to be a שבועה *shvu'ah*
and according to רב הונא *Rav Huna* every case still requires involving
the court and still requires a שבועה *shvu'ah* to make sure that
the שומר *shomer* is not holding it onto for himself. Okay so
we'll pick up with this tomorrow.